Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 10 -- Letters to Franklin, received during his residence in France ca.1776-1785 Mss.B.F85inventory10
American Philosophical Society
- Letters received during Franklin's residence in France, ca.1776-1785
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [before 1781 February 23]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Is requested by his mother to invite Franklin and his grandson to dinner. Hopes M. [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard will come with them also.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 3p.; de Lavan, Hudson
    Account of his manner of living since he left Paris; desires Franklin to forward any letters he may have received for him.
    (In French. Mutilated.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 3p.; L'héritier, -----
    Has studied for the law, but sees no prospect of advancement or gain, owing to the new regulations and restrictions imposed on young attorneys. Has thought of soliciting a position from M. de Vergennes in the Foreign Affairs Office. Thinks Franklin can help him by his influence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 After June 18]; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Sending a letter to be forwarded to Philadelphia. Plans for seeing him at Passy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Apologizing for not seeing him oftener; promising to find the missing papers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 May 4 or 11]; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Writes on behalf of a merchant at Dunkirk who desires permission to name his ship after Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Desiring news of Franklin; prevented by the inclement weather from going to Passy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Friday; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Sends a skilful artisan to repair Franklin's lamps.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [after 1780 October 8]; A.L. 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Hears that Franklin had the gout yesterday. Sends him the books he promised, two grammars and another work on language.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Sends him two petitions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Returns the English papers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    The ladies have heard that Franklin is to dine in the city; fear it would inconvenience him to go back before 5 o' clock to give them tea. Will select another day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Saw at Versailles two beautiful ladies, Mme. Dangiviller and Mme. de Flahaut, who expressed their regrets at not having seen Franklin for a long time. They have planned to call on him and ask him to tea.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Asks if he will have many guests at dinner and if he could invite the ladies who would like to dine with him before returning to Paris. Hopes his grandson will soon recover from the jaundice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Has heard that he is suffering from a cold. Sends him a package of licorice juice drops.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Asks for the loan of the Memoirs of the Academy for the year 1765.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Returns the volume of the memoirs and the Mercury of the 20th of last month; asks for the loan of yesterday's Mercury.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    His promise to give M. Arzaud a letter of introduction for London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Introducing two Polish gentlemen who wish to invite Dr. Franklin to a dinner at which several scientists will be present.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Asking Dr. Franklin if he can give him and Mme. Le Roy a place in his carriage going to Auteuil.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779? March 3]; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Returning the "Courrier de I'Europe" and offering to play him a game of chess.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Inviting him to dinner and to assist at a meeting of the Academy of Sciences.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Inquiring if there is any news from America and returning a volume of the Encyclopedia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Reminding Franklin that the Commissioners from the Academy [of Sciences] will call on him to-day to examine the apparatus invented by him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 3p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Sends a note containing particulars on "condensation of the air."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777 July 22]; A.N. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Explains how Chevalier de Kerninon's name is written and pronounced.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [After Feb.18 ]; A.N.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Hopes his gout is gone and that he and his grandson will not fail to come to dine at his house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Asks Franklin to send him for translation the discourse which he is reported to have made to the King.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Madame
    Desiring the address of Franklin's tailor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 c. Aug. 12]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Seque, Salvator
    Petition to Franklin for the prize-money to which his son Louis a cabin boy was entitled.
    A. E. by Franklin. "Give this poor man six livres."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 4p.; Le Tellier, James. Caen, Normandy
    A petition for assistance in ascertaining particulars regarding an inheritance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. in 3d P. 3p.; Liège, Louis
    Is a merchant at La Tremblade; describes the productions of his district, wines, brandies, salt, etc., and offers to fill any orders sent to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, May 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Limbourg-Hyrum-Holstein, Le Prince Comte Regnant de
    Sending him a letter from M. de Weiss, whose services he recommends to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Friday morning; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Livius, George
    Is sorry he cannot wait on Dr. Franklin on Sunday. Will call at the first opportunity to receive his commands for London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Lombart, -----
    Lost draft for sixty dollars; asks him to accept duplicates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Comte de Louitz, former Governor of San Domingo
    Called on Franklin to confer with him on different matters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [(1778?) March 24]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; de Louitz, Comte
    Makes inquiry about Franklin's health.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. in 3d P. 2p.; Matges, Arnaud
    Is a surgeon dentist, in very reduced circumstances; begs Franklin to help him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Melcher, Colonel. Paris
    Promising to wait on him that afternoon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, D.S. 1p.; Moore, James
    Oath of allegiance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A. Verses. 4p.; Morellet, abbé
    Drinking song to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Morellet, abbé
    Desires instructions as to the binding Franklin prefers for his six volumes of Memoirs of the Academy of Sciences.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Morellet, abbé
    Invites Franklin to dine with him and Chevalier de Chastellux. Sends a copy of a translation of Lord -----'s speech.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Morellet, abbé
    Sends Franklin "La Nouvelle Heloise," Will call on him before noon to-day. Abbé de la Roche is going to Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Myers, -----
    Regretting his inability to accept Franklin's polite invitation; asks for his pass and that of Mr. Martin Gaul.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Nantenville, ----- de
    Search warrant out for the arrest of the young negro now with Franklin; warns Franklin not to let him leave the house until the person claiming him has left Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 ?]; A.L.S. 2p.; Noguères, D.C. curé
    Writes on behalf of the two prisoners mentioned in the enclosed letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; O'-----, Comtesse de
    Sending her best wishes on the occassion of the New Year.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L.S. 1p.; Obenaus, Susanah
    A poor widow who begs him to make inquiries to find out whether her son, who went to America, is living or dead.
    (Mutilated.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, May 27; A.L.S. 2p.; d'Obsonville, Chevalier. Paris
    Sends Franklin his book.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Wednesday; A.L.S. 1p.; O'Connell, Mr
    Requests a quarter of an hour's audience on Friday morning about some business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Perard, -----. Paris ?
    Sending a composition of his own, written in Franklin's honor with the hope of amusing him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Perroy, Madame
    Implores Franklin's aid on behalf of her three little children, who are in danger of dying from cold and hunger.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Podmaniczky, Baron Joseph
    Asking permission to wait upon Franklin that day at dinner and to bring a friend with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 Janurary 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Poivre, Francoise Robin de livet
    Desiring Franklin's advice as to her brother's choice of a career.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. 1p.; Poivre, Françoise Robin de livet. Lyons
    She and her husband, admirers of Franklin, send him their best wishes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Powell, Jephne
    A request for Franklin's patronage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 before April 14]; A.L.S. 3p.; Raymond, ----- de
    Begging for help; served the American cause with zeal; captured by the English and held a prisoner twenty-two months; lost all his money; unable to get employment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Rentin. Mme
    Invitation to Franklin and his grandson to dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Richemont, Comte de
    Asks that the notice of the United States Government may be called to an improvement in a gun carriage made by M. Mancet, a young friend of his.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, September 9; L.S. 2p.; Robert, Madame de
    Account of her desperate situation; abandoned by her husband, deprived of her pension and in absolute want; begs for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. 1p.; Roché, -----
    Begging Franklin to obtain employment for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Tott, Baron de
    Desires to consult Franklin about an engraving of Gen. Washington; the affair left in his hands by the Marquis de la Fayette.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Rouen, Madame de
    Begs for aid in her destitute condition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S 1p.; Sabine, Baron de
    A begging letter from a brother Mason.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Sabine, Baron de
    Begging for assistance; ill, destitute and burdened with an invalid wife.
    (In French. In duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. S. 1p.; de St. Germain. -----
    Ask aid to secure a legacy left him by a relative in New York.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Salviony, -----
    A begging letter from a teacher.
    (In Latin.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L.S. 1p.; Sautier, François
    Served in Gen. [Richard] Montgomery's army; begs Franklin for assistance to reach a seaport in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Starks, Burwell. Paris
    Applies for a passport.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; St. Auban, Mme Gruyn de
    Regrets that they have an engagement for Saturday at the Marquis de Biron's. Asks Franklin and his grandson to select some day in the following week.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Stenay, Madame de
    Begs to know if M. de Montfort mentioned certain plans to the advantage of America; desires the address of the American ladies that she may interest them in her little plans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 2p.; Thuard, John. Dunkirk
    Applies to Franklin for his share of certain prize-monies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L.S. 2p.; Thomas, -----
    Is an employee of the General Control; begs Franklin to help him to obtain a position in the French West Indies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 After April 14]; A.L.S. 1p.; Cassini de Thury, ----
    M. [Jean Baptiste] Le Roy has just submitted to the Academy a work which interests him greatly. Asks Franklin if he could procure him a copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 3p.; Toscano, Jean-Louis
    Application made to Franklin as a brother Mason for aid in his abandoned and destitute state.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Verses, 2p.; Toscano, Jean-Louis
    An old man without food or shelter, begs Franklin for help.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 3p.; Trigant, -----
    Asking his intervention with M. [Antoine Raymond Jean Gualbert Gabriel] de Sartine to secure the rank of Captain for his son Jean Bart.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Troisset ?, -----
    Begging an audience; is without profession, fortune or hope.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Sending Franklin a request from Mme. Brillon; urges him to spend Saturday with her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Wednesday 7; A.L. 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Returns the writing sent him by Franklin; question of the translation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Will not go to Versailles if Franklin has heard that the Comtesse d'Artois has received the last sacraments. M. Filleul is going and would take Franklin's letter to M. de Vergennes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Inviting him to dine at Epinay with some ladies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Before May 12]; A.L. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Requesting Franklin to lend him a book entitled "Memoire sur les conducteurs."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Asking Franklin what the Countess of Brionne wanted to see him (Le Veillard) about.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 ? Dec.]; A.N. 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Sending [Denis] Diderot's book "L'interpretation de la Nature" and referring to several passages in it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    With reference to Franklin's visit to the library of St. Genevieve.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Requesting Franklin to forward a letter to England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Veillard, Mlle
    Called to see Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; "Vestatur."
    Announcement of two chemical processes. The former relates to artificial production of gold, the latter to that of silver. 'Offers his discoveries for sale.
    (In German.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 After December 8]; A.L.S. 3p.; Vincent, Pomponne
    Requests Franklin's opinion of a work on the relations between England and America written by him, and which he wishes to publish.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777 C August 25]; Various Persons
    Bills and business memoranda.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 17; Various Persons
    Proposals for furnishing military stores, arms, ammunition, clothing, etc., to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 3p. 7p.; Various Persons
    List of bills drawn upon [John] Adams from July 6, 1780, to January 27, 1781.
    (In duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 2p.; Various Persons
    Schedule of fifty sets of bills of exchange amounting to 2,400,000 livres and of six sets for the interest at 6 per cent., amounting to 144,000.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 2p.; Various Persons
    List of cases containing articles for Dr. Franklin, the Duke de Chaulnes, Mr. Vaughan, etc., Shipped from England to Paris via Ostend.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 2p.; Various Persons
    List of cases containing articles for Dr. Franklin, the Duke de Chaulnes, Mr. Vaughan, etc., shipped from England to Paris via Ostend.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Printed N.S. 1p. each.; Various Persons
    Notices of the meetings of the Lodge of Neuf Soeurs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Printed N.S. 3p.; Various Persons
    Letters to members of the Lodge of Neuf Soeurs, with list of Officers for 1782, 1785, 1786.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Various Persons
    Social notes, conveying bits of news, requesting engagements, offering congratulations, etc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Various Persons
    Inquiries after Dr. Franklin's health, and requests and information of various kinds.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Various Persons
    Invitations to participate in Charity Meetings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Printed N. 1p. in 3d P.; Various Persons
    Marriage notices.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777 June 14]; Various Persons.; de Sarsfield, Vicomte
    Invitations to breakfast, dinner, tea, concerts, to play chess, etc.
    Re: Social Invitations.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Various Persons
    Replies to invitations.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Various Persons
    Visiting Cards.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Various Persons
    Tradesmen's cards.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Various Persons
    Miscellaneous notes and addresses.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Tuesday morning; L. in 3d P. 1p.; -------, -------
    Note telling of Mme. Helétius's condition. Was very ill, suffering from high fever, cough, etc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Wednesday morning; L. in 3d. P. 1p.; -------, -------
    Mme. Helvétius's illness; her condition that morning and the treatment applied.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; La Roche, Abbé de
    Mme. Helvétius's condition is better to-day, after having been so serious yesterday as to alarm her two friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Tuesday, 4 O'clock; L. 1p.; ------, -------
    "The mother" thanks Franklin and the children bless him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; -----, -----
    Is very desirous to dine with him to-morrow, but fears weather will prevent. If his carriage comes to Paris in the morning, it might take her and the young lady with her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; -----, -----
    Inquiring if Franklin will be at home Friday evening. Count de Duprat, Abbé Palasseau and Père Caillot wish to pay him a visit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Wednesday; A.L. 1p.; -----, -----. Chaillot
    Has just come back from the country. Very anxious to see Franklin. Asks him what day he can invite her to dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; -----, -----
    Asks Franklin if the papers she is sending him are of any value and if the person to whom they belong can expect to get any money for them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Mountmorres, Lord
    Informs him that he leaves Paris on Thursday, and will be happy to execute any commands he has for England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. 2p.; Helvétius, Mme
    The nice sayings in Franklin's letter made her more regretful at not having been able to dine with him. Hopes to receive good news today about his health.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A. Poem. 1p.; -----, -----
    Grateful America to to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. and Poem. 3p.; -----, -----
    A tribute to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Verses. 1p.; -----, -----
    "My surprise" —homage to Franklin—expresses surprise at having seen Franklin in pleasure resorts and applauding the dancers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Poem. 7p.; -----, -----
    The Muse of America. An ode to Dr. Franklin on the War of Independence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Verses. 1p.; -----, -----
    Advice to Dr. Franklin not to heed the homages of the fickle multitude and to show himself less.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Verses 2p.; Verses, -----
    To Dr. Franklin recalling his planting of a tree during a reception given to him by the Comtesse d'Houdetot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Verses. 1p.; -----, -----
    Eulogy of Marquis de la Fayette and his cruise during the war in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 1p.; -----, -----
    Announcing the establishment of a school for English and American girls in Paris and requesting him to recommend it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 4p.; -----, -----
    He dedicated his book "Texte de la Nature Rétabli" to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 C; L. 2p.; -----, -----
    Concerning the fitting out of vessels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; -----, -----
    A recipe for the mixture of nitre and antimony.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 April 3]; L. 2p.; -----, -----. Bayonne
    Urges Dr. Franklin to propose to Messrs. [Silas] Deane and [Arthur] Lee that red wine and brandy be exported to the Colonies in exchange for tobacco.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 25p.; -----, -----
    Key to Cipher Code.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; -----, -----
    Tells where Briere, a geographical engineer, studied, and gives his qualifications.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 1p.; -----, -----
    Requesting Dr. Franklin to recommend Court de Trumbinsky to people in the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. 1p.; -----, -----
    Requesting Franklin to give his approbation to a History of America written by him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 1p.; -----, -----
    Thinks it very essential to have the translation of this exquiste piece promptly published.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. 1p.; -----, -----
    Is not acquainted with the manner of making out memorials. Cannot say whether the enclosed one will answer the purpose. Will call on him to-morrow and confer about it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. 1p.; -----, -----
    Refusing to do business with a firm. (in England).